<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The brideling, sadling and ryding, of a rich churle in Hampshire, by the subtill practise of one Iudeth Philips, a professed cunning woman, or fortune teller VVith a true discourse of her vnwomanly vsing of a trype wife, a widow, lately dwelling on the back side of S. Nicholas shambles in London, whom she with her conferates, likewise cosoned: for which fact, shee was at the Sessions house without New-gate arraigned, where she confessed the same, and had iudgement for her offence, to be whipped through the citie, the 14. of February, 1594.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110442</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845984</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845984</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10918</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09574)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10918)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 349:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The brideling, sadling and ryding, of a rich churle in Hampshire, by the subtill practise of one Iudeth Philips, a professed cunning woman, or fortune teller VVith a true discourse of her vnwomanly vsing of a trype wife, a widow, lately dwelling on the back side of S. Nicholas shambles in London, whom she with her conferates, likewise cosoned: for which fact, shee was at the Sessions house without New-gate arraigned, where she confessed the same, and had iudgement for her offence, to be whipped through the citie, the 14. of February, 1594.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T[homas] C[reede] and are to be solde by William Barley, at his shop in New-gate Market, neare Christ-Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England --  Social life and customs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10918:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10918:1"/>
            <p>THE Brideling, Sadling and Ryding, of a rich Churle in Hampſhire, by the ſubtill practiſe of one Iudeth Philips, a profeſſed cunning woman, or Fortune teller.</p>
            <p>VVith a true diſcourſe of her vnwomanly vſing of a Trype wife, a widow, lately dwelling on the back ſide of S. Nicholas ſhambles in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, whom ſhe with her conferates, likewiſe coſoned:</p>
            <p>For which fact, ſhee was at the Seſſions houſe without New-gate arraigned, where ſhe confeſſed the ſame, and had iudgement for her offence, to be whipped through the Citie, the 14. of February, 1594.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed at London by T.C. and are to be ſolde by William Barley, at his ſhop in New-gate Market, neare Chriſt-Church. 1595.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="story">
            <pb facs="tcp:10918:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10918:2"/>
            <head>A true diſcouerie of diuers notable villanies practiſed by one Iudeth Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips the wife of Iohn Philips, of Crowne Alley in Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops gate ſtreete, the like was neuer in any age committed by a woman.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all the ſeuen deadly ſinnes, there is none ſo common in this flouriſhing Realme of England, as is the gréeuous ſin of Covetouſneſſe, for it is the roote of all iniquitie, the puddle of perdition, and the alluring bayt of hell, and that minde which is once drowned in the depth of that ſin, is ſold to eternall damnation, vnleſſe the mercy of God raiſe him vp from that filthie and deuouring gulphe: for there is no ſin committed vnder the cope of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, but one braunch of Couetouſneſſe is therein compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended. As Vſury, what is it but the deſire of gold, and hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp of wealth? What is Whoredome and Lecherie, but luſt and deſire of the fleſh? What is Drunkenneſſe but Couetouſneſſe of wine? And what is Pride, Enuy, Fury, Theft, Murther, but the deſires of the wicked minde? yea euery vice is cloaked vnder the winges of Couetouſneſſe. The théefe and robber both by ſea and land, ventureth the hazarding of his life for couetouſneſſe of wealth: yea all creatures which beare life, in ſome ſort cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t after vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things. Lucifer that once was an Angel of brightneſſe, through his pride coueted to ſitte in the bright celeſtiall throne of God, for which he was caſt from heauen, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10918:3"/>made an Angell of darkeneſſe. Wée may reade how <hi>Ieza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell</hi> for coueting poore <hi>Nabothes</hi> Vineyard, for the which, by the iuſt iudgements of God ſhée was deuoured of filthy Dogges. Therefore the ſinne of Couetouſneſſe is ſo ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous before the face of heauen, that God in his tenth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement ſtrickly doeth charge vs to forſake all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull couetouſneſſe, by theſe wordes; Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbors houſe, thou ſhalt not couet thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors wife, nor his ſeruaunt, nor his mayde, nor his oxe, nor his aſſe, nor anie thing that is his. Which precept, if men woulde aduiſedly and carefully looke into, and with their true endeuoures ſéeke to followe it, we ſhould not haue in this our Realme of Englande, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this famous Cittie of London, ſo many badde and notorious members yearely cut off by the Quéenes maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Lawes as wée continually haue. Which ſpectacle, wée haue once euerie moneth to ſee and beholde, to the great heartes griefe of all her maieſties louing ſubiectes: but yet men are graceleſſe and wilfully minded, and will not be warned, nor take example by the downfal of others: ſome are ſo idlely brought vp, that they can nor will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure no labour; and ſome are ſo haughtie and proud min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that they ſcorne to bende their neckes to the yoake of others, and liue honeſtly, in taking paines for their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, but ſtudie and deuiſe night and day how they may frawdulently and deceitfully better their eſtates by the ſweate of other mens browes, for now a dayes, theft, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, robberies, and vnlawfull practiſes are ſo common, that not onely men, but women and children, ſtriue with ſtudying and buſie braines, how to compaſſe and bring to paſſe many cunning ſleites and pollicies, to deceiue the world. As by an example here following, is truly deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by a woman, the mirror and mappe of all coſonage and deceit, whereat all modeſt women may bluſh, and euerie true meaning man may ſmile at the folly of the worlde.</p>
            <p>Pardon my penne, you modeſt Dames and graue Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:10918:3"/>it ſhall no way impaire your honourable Sexe, but truly imblazen to the worlde, the couſoning deuiſes of a ſhameleſſe woman, whoſe name and conuerſation hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter followeth.</p>
            <p>This is to let you vnderſtand, that in the moneth of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary laſt paſt, in the famous Cittie of London, one <hi>Iudeth Philips</hi> the wife of <hi>Iohn Philips,</hi> by occupation a Cun-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, now dwelling in Crown Alley in Biſhops gate ſtréet, was brought before her Mateſties Juſtices of peace at the Seſſions houſe in olde Baily, and there was indited vpon coſonage, where ſhée confeſſed the truth of all her practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, before the honourable Lords of the bench. But know gentle Reader, before I vndertake to explaine the truth of all her practiſes done here in London, I will firſt in moſt ample manner, ſet foorth to the view of the worlde, a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table villany committed by this cunning and fine witted woman, in the village of <hi>Vpsborne</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> in diſtaunce ſeuen myles or thereaboutes from <hi>VVinche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Iudeth Philips</hi> before times hauing another huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band named Pope, being an honeſt poore man of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation and well beloued amongſt his neighbours, but this his wife not contented with his poore eſtate of liuing, vppon a certaine time tooke an occaſion to goe away from him, and purpoſed to ſéeke ſome other courſe for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of her liuing, ſo trauelling along the Weſt parts of Englande, it was her chaunce to remaine for a certaine ſpace in the pariſh of <hi>Vpsbrne,</hi> a Towne ſeituate and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Hampeſhire,</hi> and there practiſed many couſoning ſleites and deuiſes to deceiue the ſimpler ſort of people in the Countrey: Onely ſhée betooke her ſelfe to the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a cunning woman, a Fortune teller, and thoſe which ſhée knew did abounde in wealth, ſhée daily ſought meanes to bring into a fooles paradice, and by one deuice or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:10918:4"/>other, cozen them of ſome ſtore of Crownes. Not far from this Towne, there was dwelling a wealthy churle, (whoſe name I here omit) that was ſomewhat fantaſticall and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to beléeue euery tale he heard, which Churles wealth whetted ſo the deſire of this woman, that ſhe deuiſed a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till practiſe to haue a ſhare out of his Cofers. Firſt to bring her purpoſe to effect, ſhe enquired ſecretly of his neighbors of what condition and conuerſation this myzer and his wife were of, and in what ſtate the maner of his liuing lay, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhe vnderſtood, that this Churle was in ſute of lawe about a péece of ground, with one ſir <hi>William Kingſman,</hi> a worſhipfull Knight in <hi>Hamſhire,</hi> which being done, this <hi>Iudeth Philips</hi> one euening very late went into the backe ſide of this mans houſe, where vnder a hollow holly frée ſhe buried an angell of gold, and ſixe pence in white mony, and then returned home to her lodging againe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night: But the next day after, ſhe walked by the Churles houſe, and it fortuned that his wife ſat at her doore to take the freſh aire, and ſo when this cunning witted woman ſawe her time, ſtood ſtill, and lookt very wiſhly vpon her, which made the Churles wife to maruell much, that a ſtrange woman whom ſhe neuer ſaw before, ſhould looke vpon her ſo ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly, which cauſed her to demaund wherefore ſhe lookt ſo earneſtly in her face? O miſtreſſe ſaid this <hi>Iudeth Philips,</hi> you are the fortunates woman I ſaw this many a day, for in your browes I ſée good fortune ſit, haue you not (ſaid ſhe) a hollow holly trée ſtanding near vnto your houſe, with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine wéedes growing about the roote? we haue (anſwered the mizers wife) and what of that? O miſtreſſe ſaid this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man then, if I might ſpeake with your huſband, and if hée be like you in the face, you will come to be excéeding rich, for vnder that hollow trée there is great ſtore of treaſure hid, come in (then ſaid ſhe) and thou ſhalt ſee my huſband: but when this woman came into the place where her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was, ſhe likewiſe lookt him ſtrangely in the face, and told him that ſhe knew by certaine ſignes in his forehead,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:10918:4"/>that he was in ſute of lawe with ſome great man of that country, and how he ſhould preuaile in his ſute. Alſo ſhe told him, if he would be at ſome charge, ſhe would bring him to great ſummes of gold and ſiluer, that was hidden about his grounds, to whom the man being ſome what couetous ſaid; If I might firſt ſée ſomething of thy ſkill, I will be at any charge thou wilt, but firſt tell me what thou art, and from whence thou cammeſt? I am ſaid this <hi>Iudeth,</hi> an Engliſh woman borne, but come new from the Pope, and knowe more of his mind then any woman in the world: to confirm her words for truth, ſhe tooke her oath vpon the Bible how that ſhe came from the Pope: which was true, for her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands name as then was Pope, which being done, ſhe tooks him by the hand and led him to the roote of the hollow trée, where ſhe cauſed him to dig till he found ſome gold, which was the angell and the ſixe pence, which the night before ſhe cloſely hid, this brought the couetous Churle into ſuch a conceit, that he promiſed to giue her whatſoeuer ſhe deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſo that her promiſe might be performed: then ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of him for her paines, fouretéene pounds, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at he grumbled to loſe ſo great a gub at one time, yet at laſt the hope of the treaſure hidden vnder the trée made him to conſent, and ſo with ſpéede gaue this woman fouretéene poundes in ready gold and ſiluer. Then ſaid this woman, now muſt I haue the largeſt chamber in your houſe behu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with the fineſt linnen you can get, ſo that nothing about your chamber but white linnen cloth be ſéen, then muſt you ſet fiue candelſticks in fiue ſeuerall places in your Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and vnder euery candelſticke you muſt put an angel of gold, all which was done as ſhe required: and likewiſe ſaid ſhe, you muſt alſo get a ſaddle and a bridle with two new girths thereunto; all which the couetous churle performed in hope to attaine to great wealth: then this <hi>Iudeth</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him and his wife to go into the yard, where ſhe ſet the ſaddle on his back, and theron girteth it faſt with two new girths, and alſo put a bridle vpon his head, all which being
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10918:5"/>done, ſhe gat vppon his backe in the ſaddle, and ſo rid him thrée times betwixt the chamber &amp; the holly trée, then ſaid this coſoning queane, you muſt lye thrée houres one by an other groueling on your bellies vnder this trée, &amp; ſtir not I charge you, vntill I come backe againe, for I muſt go into the Chamber to méete the Quéene of Fairies and welcome her to that holy and vnſpotted place, ſo this churle and his wife were left quaking in the colde, caſting many a long looke for the comming of this woman, but ſhe in the meane time tooke downe all the fine linnen clothes from the wals of the chamber and wrapt them vp cloſe in a bundle, and all the gold from vnder the candelſticks, and put them into her purſe, then putting her ſelfe into a faire white ſmock, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what diſguiſed, with a thing on her head all white, and a ſtick in her hand, ſhe appeared vnto him and his wife, vſing ſome valliance, as old wiues ſay, ſpirits with night ſpelles do, ſhe vaniſhed away, and againe entered the chamber where her packe laie ready, and ſo roundly went away, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the churle and his wife in their cold lodging, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore foole ſawe the time expired, and his exſpected wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man did not return, he got him vp and caſt off his ſaddle and bridle, being halfe dead with colde, retired into the chamber where he ſuppoſed to haue found this cunning woman tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with the Quéene of Fairies, but when he entered his chamber, and ſaw both his linnen and his gold conuaide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, fel into ſuch a perplexity of mind, as though he had bin diſtraight of his wits: one while gréeuing for the loſſe of his fouretéene pounds, another while, for the abuſe of his good name, likewiſe for the penance and diſgrace ſhe put him and his wife vnto, the baſe and rediculous maner of his ſadling, his cold lodging and weary time ſpent vnder the trée, to his vtter infamy and ſhame. And laſtly, the loſſe of his pure and fine linnen, but yet he diſſembled his griefe in ſuch order, that his neighbors had no ſuſpition therof, ſo in all haſte, hée take horſe, and road to <hi>VVincheſter,</hi> being in diſtance ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen miles from the towne where he dwelt, and there certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10918:5"/>a kinſman of his, of all the actions before happened: to betwixt this Churle and his kinſman, they made hew and try after her, by which this deceitfull woman was taken, and conueyed to priſon, where ſhe remained vntil the great Aſſiſes came: and for the ſame was arraigned before the right honorable my Lord <hi>Anderſon,</hi> the Lord chief Iuſtice of the Common place vnder her Maieſtie by his Office, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom, ſhe confeſſed her ſelfe guiltie of all theſe afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid practiſes, and there receiued ſuch deſerued puniſhment as the law would permit. But this ſhameleſſe woman-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding neither her publike diſgrace, nor the puniſhments of heauen inflicted vpon all ſuch graceleſſe liuers, putting off the garment of ſhamefaſtneſſe, and forgetting her ſelfe to haue done any ſuch thing, drownde her ſelfe in the ſea of all vices, and the gulphe of all outragious miſchiefes: for ſhe after this, growing careleſſe of her good name, fell into company of two certaine bad minded men, of the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and quallitie ſhe was on, whoſe names I here omit: but the one of them was in his former time, by trade a ſilk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weauer, but leauing that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt courſe of liuing, betooke himſelfe to a very wicked diſpoſition, as to build the ſtate of his liuing vpon coſonage, and to blind the eies of the world, goes in the habit of a Lawier all in black, like a ciuill Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman. The other fine witted companion, in the attire of a Country Gentleman, I will not ſay, he dwels at <hi>Borden</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> nor his wife is the owner of a fewe Chery-trées, the onely ſtaie and maintenance of both their liuings, but to be plaine, theſe two Caterpillers <hi>P.</hi> and <hi>V.</hi> like Wolues in ſhéepes cloathing, feedes vpon the blouds of many innocent lambes, who knowing a woman, her huſband being dead, and ſhe left a rich widow, and in the way of marriage, wold neuer ceaſe pondering in their craftie brains, till they were throughly acquainted with her, and ſo by one ſly deuiſe or other, ouerreach her for ſom part of hir ſubſtance, they made her beléeue, they could help her to a huſband of mightie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenewes and great wealth, where at laſt ſhe found them
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10918:6"/>but Caterpillers to liue vpon her labors. As for example, the notable péece of villany committed betwixt theſe two counterfeit gentlemen <hi>P.</hi> and <hi>V.</hi> and this coſoning woman <hi>Iudith Philips,</hi> of a Trype wife, lately dwelling on the back ſide of S. Nicholas ſhambles in London, as it was truly noted at the arraignment of the ſaid <hi>Iudith Philips,</hi> the <hi>14.</hi> of February laſt paſt, <hi>1594.</hi> at the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions houſe in the old Baily, before my Lord <hi>Anderſon,</hi> and others of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Iuſtices, and likewiſe word by word, as the ſaid <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith</hi> confeſt it her ſelfe in the priſon of Newgate, where ſhe now remaineth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="story">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:10918:6"/>
            <head>A diſcouerie of the Coſoning and ill hardling of the Trype wife, by Iudeth Philips and her confederates.</head>
            <figure/>
            <p>THere was of late dwelling in London on the back ſide of the ſhambles, a very rich and wealthy man of good conuerſation, who dying, left his w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe in ſuch good eſtate of liuing, as fewe of the trade of ſelling Trypes, might well compate with her. This woman as it was well knowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt her neighbors, had many ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors in the way of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and many of ſufficient liuings, which womans name for her wealth, was bruted through euery part of the citie, ſo that it came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt to the eares of theſe two coſoning com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, <hi>P.</hi> and <hi>V.</hi> who ſtudied day and night how they might come acquainted with this rich trype wife, ſo that at laſt, this practiſe they deuiſed.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:10918:7"/>
            <p>This <hi>P.</hi> being a very comely man of perſonage, and of a Gentleman like qualitie, went as a ſuter among the reſt, vnto this widow, wherby he learned the condition and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the woman; and what large proffers ſhe had in the way of marriage, likewiſe he vnderſtood how that a weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Cittizen dwelling vpon London Bridge, had receiued from her in pledge of loue, a Ring with fiue Diamonds in it, being in value worth fiue poundes, which Ring vppon ſome diſagréement, ſhe receiued againe: alſo this <hi>P.</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that one maiſter <hi>Grace</hi> a gentleman, dwelling in <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi> was her deare friend, and one that was her councellor in all her actions, and how that ſhe would not do any thing without his conſent, and how that ſometimes he ledged in the widowes houſe, which things being well conſidered off betwixt theſe two fine witted fellowes, whoſe heads being neuer barraine, deuiſed a preſent pollicie to deceiue this couetous Trype wife. Firſt they made priuy to their prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes this <hi>Iudeth Philips</hi> before named, &amp; told her the ſtate, condition, and qualitie of this widow, and made her the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of their intended driſt, who was as ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance therof, as they were craftie in deuiſing, then they made a counterfeit Letter from maiſter <hi>Grace,</hi> being as then in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and ſent as it were from him to this widow of London, by this <hi>Iudeth Philips,</hi> wherin was conteined, how that ſhe was a wiſe woman, and could tel fortunes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted her to welcome her to her houſe, and to make much of her, for ſhe might ſtand her in great ſtead, which Letter being in good maner contriued, as beſt befitting their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, cauſed this <hi>Iudeth Philippes</hi> to be attired in a ruſlet gown like a country woman, and to bear this Letter home to the widowes houſe behind the ſhambles, where ſhe was no ſooner come, &amp; the Letter read, but was bid welcome for M <hi>Graces</hi> ſake, but eſpecially for the ſecret quallities the which her friend did commend her in: but now when this diſſembling minion eſpied her time, ſhe requeſted to ſee the widowes hand, which ſhe vouchſafe to do; O miſtreſſe (then
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10918:7"/>ſaid this woman) I ſée by the Art of Palmiſtrie in your hand, and by mine owne ſkill, that you are borne to good fortune, likewiſe I know you haue had many rich proffers in the way of marriage: I haue had ſaid the widow indeed, Knights fellowes come vnto me. Then ſaid this deceifull woman againe, a Citizen dwelling vpon London Bridge, hath bin an earneſt ſuter vnto you, and hath receiued a ring with fiue Diamonds in pledge of loue, but the Ring you haue againe. And ſo there was another Gentleman loued you well, which once would haue kiſſed you, and vſed you harſhly, by that token in ſtriuing with him, your hatſell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sowſe Tub. At which words, ſaid the Trype wife, I thinke you know all things. I know ſome what replied this woman again, haue you not miſtreſſe about your houſe a great rumbling when you are in bed? Sometimes ſayd the widow we haue: By that ſaid this woman again, your huſband in his life hid about your houſe great ſtore of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for which cauſe there are ſprites now that haunt your houſe: when indéed the noiſe which ſhe heard, was no other but this <hi>P.</hi> and <hi>V.</hi> that late in the nights would lember againſt her doore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd likewiſe in the mornings. But mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe if you wil be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t ſome charge, I wil ſhew you where this gold and filt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r is hid. I will good woman, be at any charge thou wilt with reaſon, ſo I may gaine therby. Then ſayd this coſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ning D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nie, you muſt ſet fiue Candelſtickes, and fiue candels burning in them, in fiue corners of your houſe, then muſt you car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtly pray in euery cerner a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſpace, which was performed with all all ſpéed. Thus is Gods word made a cloake for all ſuch diuiliſh practiſes, onely to blinde the eyes of the ſimple and well meaning people. But God ſurely in diuers places of the ſcriptures ſaith; That whoſoeuer beleeueth in Witches and Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, beléeue in the Diuel: but yet God doth ſuffer the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel and his Angelles to ſpread abroad the worlde, to tempt thoſe that be weake in faith, and like Wolues in ſheepes cloathing, ſéeke to deuour vs.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:10918:8"/>
            <p>But now to our purpoſe again: This craftie creature cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Trype wife from her prayers, aſked her what ſhee ſaw, and what ſhe heard? to whom ſhe anſwered, that ſhée heard nothing. Then ſaid this minion againe, you muſt fetch as much Cold, Rings, Iewels, and Chaines, to the value of one hundreth poundes, and put them into a purſe, all which was done: then ſhée tooke the purſe with the gold and wound about it a bottome of woollen yarne, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, ſhe requeſted the widow to goe a while from hir, ſo in the meane ſpace, like a craftie queane ſhée conueyed the gold into her pocket, and tooke another bottom of yarne with two ſtones in it, in the ſame likeneſſe the ether was off, and gaue it the woman againe, as though it had bin the very ſame: to whom ſhe ſaid, I pray you miſtreſſe lock this vp very ſure, and looke not into it vntill I come againe, for I muſt goe and conuerſe with a wiſe man that is acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Quéen of Fairies, but I requeſt you, that you will ſend him by me, a fat Turkey, and a couple of Capons, onely to get his friendſhip in the matter, and no doubt but we ſhall finde the hid treaſure very ſhortly: which woman, through couetouſneſſe of this money, went preſently and bought a Turky, &amp; two fat Capons, and ſent them with this coſoning cheater by her mayd ſeruant, into Holb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rn, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come neare vnto the place whither ſhe intended to goe, tooke them from the mayd, &amp; ſo ſent her back againe. Thus this daintie witted Dame, hauing coſoned the trype wife, of all her gold, Iewels, &amp; Chaines, returned ioyfully vnto the lodgings of her two ſchoolemaiſters, <hi>P.</hi> and <hi>V.</hi> who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her come, aſked her preſently if ſhe had ſped? I haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered ſhe, in ſom ſort for here is a hundred pound to make vs merry with, the which they diuided into ſoure parts: ſhe receiued two for her paines, and they betwixt them the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two, and afterwards made merry with the widowes Turkey, and her couple of Capons, and ſo went with fiftie poundes home to her huſband <hi>Iohu Philips,</hi> dwelling in Crowne Alley in Biſhoppes gate ſtreete: who noting her
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10918:8"/>long abſence, and diuers ſtarts ſhe made from him, aſked where ſhe had bene, and how ſhe came by that money? to whom ſhée gaue many hard words and bad anſweres, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that in his anger he ſtrooke hir, but yet by no means he could do, the craftie queane wold reueale where ſhe had it. But now to returne to the widowes mayd again, who comming out of Holborne home ſo her miſtreſſe, tolde her that ſhe ſuſpected the queane had coſoned her, with that ſhée went preſently and vnwound the bottome of yarne, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhée founde nothing but two ſtones: the which being done, ſhee went to one of her neighbours and diſcourſt to him all the maner of her coſoning, but he lyke a wiſe man, counſelled her not to make hue and cry, but watch a time vntill ſhe came againe, and then to apprehend her. Not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dayes after this, theſe three aforeſayd coſoning compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, met againe togither, and conſulted how they might get a another bootie of this trype wife, which was platted downe in this manner. Firſt this <hi>Iudeth Philips</hi> ſhould repaire vnto the widow againe, and tell her that ſhe came from the Quéene of Fairits, and how that ſhée gaue her in charge (if ſhée woulde attaine the hidden treaſure) to ſet twelue Candelſtickes in diuerſe places of her houſe, and vnder euery Candelſticke both golde and ſiluer, and to ſet all her plate rounde about the Candles, whereby this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till headed woman might the eaſier deceiue her of it: but comming to the widowes houſe againe, ſhée was bidden welcome as before, and requeſted to come in, but in the meane time, thy Conſtable was ſent for, and ſhée appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and ſo carried to Newgate. Likewiſe for the ſame fact, her huſband was arraigned before the be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch but found not guiltie, and ſo quit by the Iewrie: but the lawe fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her guiltie therin, was returned ſo Newgate, where the did remaine till the Seſſions following for iudgement: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that time being c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me, her iudgement was, to be whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped through the citie. Thus haue you heard y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> notable prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes committed by this woman and her aſſociates. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o doubt but there are mo ſuch wicked members in this land.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10918:9"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of England <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, then do you ſhew your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnto your Countrey, and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruice vnto your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eue: For whoſe long and quiet raig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, let all true ſubiects daily pray. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10918:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
